{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "While deployed to Fort Bliss, this man’s wife and children tragically died in a fire in San Francisco. Charles Stanton, this man’s personal aide, recorded him as saying “Lafayette, we are here” during a visit to Lafayette’s tomb in Paris. This man was allowed to design his own insignia, choosing four gold stars, after being promoted to General of the Armies. For ten points, name this commander of the American Expeditionary Forces during World War I, a general nicknamed “Black Jack.”",
      "answer": "John J. Pershing"
    },
    {
      "question": "This person created a polar area diagram divided into months, known as the “Rose” diagram. The run-down facilities at Selimiye prompted this person to work with Isambard Brunel to create Renkioi, a facility that lessened mortality rates by 90%. At this person’s request, Scutari hospital was investigated by the Sanitary Commission. This person’s treatment of wounded soldiers led her to be known as the “Lady with the Lamp.” For ten points, name this nurse active in the Crimean War.",
      "answer": "Florence Nightingale"
    },
    {
      "question": "Manco Yapanqui failed to capture this city after a ten-month siege, despite possessing over two hundred thousand soldiers. This city’s Church of Santo Domingo was built atop the ruins of the Temple of the Sun after its destruction. One ruler was locked in this city’s “Ransom Room”after being ambushed at nearby Cajamarca by conquistadors. Atahualpa was strangled to death by Francisco Pizarro in, for ten points, what former capital city of the Incan Empire?",
      "answer": [
        "Cuzco or Qusqu",
        "Qosqo"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A science fiction author from this country depicted an invasion of aliens known as Trisolarans in his “Remembrance of Earth’s Past” series. One author from this country found inspiration for a novel after being falsely diagnosed with lung cancer. Novels from this country include The Republic of Wine and Soul Mountain. The Red Detachment of Women was one of the Eight Model Works of this country’s communist government. For ten points, name this country, home of Liu Cixin and Gao Xingjian.",
      "answer": [
        "People’s Republic of China",
        "PRC,",
        "Zhonghua Renmin Guo, do not prompt on",
        "“Republic of China”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man issued the Code of the Rayas to improve the plight of Christians working on Sipahi farms. After forming the “Unholy Alliance” with Francis I, this man sent the corsair Hayreddin Barbarossa to patrol European waters. This man worked with Ebussuud Effendi in order to reconcile the Kanun code with Sha’ria, earning the title Lawgiver. For ten points, identify this longest reigning Ottoman sultan who brought the empire to its territorial height.",
      "answer": [
        "Suleiman the Magnificent",
        "Suleiman I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During the debates over this agreement, Henry S. Foote drew a pistol on Thomas Hart Benton over a plan proposed by a “Committee of Thirteen.” Charles Jenkins’ Georgia Platform promised “no further assaults” on rights as long as this agreement was in place. The boundaries of Texas were set by this agreement in exchange for the assumption of $10 million of debt. Trading slaves in Washington D.C. was made illegal by, for ten points, what series of five bills negotiated by Henry Clay that eased tensions between slave and free states?",
      "answer": "Compromise of 1850"
    },
    {
      "question": "A prelude to this effort was calculated by Reginald Waite and run by Sir Brian Robertson, who proposedthiseffort.Thiseffort’splannersincludedAlbertWedermeyer,whousedhisexpertiseintraveling over the “Hump.” A dispute over the introduction of a new currency into the Allied Occupation Zone prompted this effort. This effort, codenamed Operation Vittles, delivered 13,000 tons of supplies daily. For ten points, name this 1948 crisis where the RAF and USAAF supplied a German city.",
      "answer": [
        "Berlin Airlift",
        "Berlin Blockade"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This monarch lost the Battle of Langside to the Earl of Moray after being forced to abdicate and escaping imprisonment at Loch Leven Castle. Letters sent from this person to the Earl of Bothwell, the Casket Letters, might imply this person killed her husband Lord Darnley. The Bond of Association gave precedent to execute this Catholic monarch supported in the Rising of the North for her role in the Babington Plot. For ten points, name this Stuart queen executed by Elizabeth I.",
      "answer": [
        "Mary, Queen of Scotland",
        "Mary, Queen of Scots,"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The goals of this period were changed in the “Reverse Course” which instead aimed to create a strong industrial base. The Recreation and Amusement Association was created during this period to oversee legalized prostitution and reduce the incidents of rape. This period was ended by the San Francisco Peace Treaty which restored sovereignty to a certain nation except for the Ryukyu Islands. The MacArthur Constitution was drafted during, for ten points, what post-World War II period in which an East Asian nation was occupied by the United States?",
      "answer": "occupation of Japan"
    },
    {
      "question": "Inscriptions at this site tell of a visit from the monk Ukondafu Kazufusa, who confused this site with the Jetavana Garden. The city of Thom became the new capital after the Chams sacked this site in the 12th century, while the Bayon replaced this site as state temple. Originally dedicated to Vishnu by Suryavarman II, this site was eventually converted to a Buddhist temple. For ten points, identify this Khmer religious site that appears on the Cambodian flag.",
      "answer": "Angkor Wat"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2004, Jacques Chirac ordered the destruction of this country’s air force after 9 French peacekeepers were killed in Bouak´e. The Linas-Marcoussis Agreement failed to end a civil war in this country which began after the RDR’s candidate was disqualified by the FPI’s leader. Henri Konan B´edi´e ruled this country after the death of its longtime first president Felix Houphou¨et-Boigny. Laurent Gbagbo led, for ten points, what West African country home to Yamoussoukro and Abidjan?",
        "answer": [
          "Ivory Coast",
          "Cote D’Ivoire"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The disqualification of this current president of Cote D’Ivoire from the 2000 presidential election contributed to the outbreak of the Ivorian Civil War.",
        "answer": "Alassane Ouattara"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A reference to one painting of this person in Natsume Soseki’s Grass Pillow popularized that painting in Japan. Salvador Dali made a 1973 etching of this person in response to that painting, which also may have influenced a John Waterhouse painting of this person in a white and gold dress putting red poppies in her hair. This person’s dress temporarily keeps her afloat in one painting based on a scene related by Queen Gertrude. John Everett Millais painted, for ten points, what character from Hamlet as she drowns.",
        "answer": "Ophelia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Partially responding to Millais’ Ophelia, Dali wrote that this movement, which Millais and Waterhouse belonged to, painted women “the most desirable and most frightening in existence,” in an essay on this movement’s “spectral surrealism” and “eternal feminine.”",
        "answer": "Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s father was taken hostage by a group of students including Samuel L. Jackson during his father’s term as trustee for Morehouse College. Marcus Wayne Chenault stated “all Christians are my enemies” after killing this man’s mother in 1974. In this man’s final speech, he spoke of “public servants, who happen to be sanitation workers.” This man’s wife was nearly killed by a bomb in 1956 which targeted their Montgomery home. For ten points, name this Civil Rights leader who was assassinated in 1968 by James Earl Ray.",
        "answer": [
          "Martin Luther King Jr.",
          "MLK"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "King was crusading for the rights of sanitation workers in this city when he died. The location of his assassination, the Lorraine Motel, is now the National Civil Rights Museum.",
        "answer": "Memphis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This organization is a militant wing of the Deobandi revivalist movement. This organization’s leadership structure is modeled on the jirga tribal council. The “Airlift of Evil” saved many of this organization’s leaders from Kunduz. This organization drew largely from Pashtun students and was led by Mullah Omar until 2013. For 10 points, name this Sunni fundamentalist group whose control over Afghanistan was the target of 2001’s Operation Enduring Freedom.",
        "answer": "The Taliban"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ongoing peace talks between the Taliban and the United States until recently excluded representatives from this current president of Afghanistan’s government.",
        "answer": "Ashraf Ghani"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "TheDukeofBuckinghamfailedtorelievethesiegeofonecityaffectedbythislaw.CardinalRichelieu’s siege of La Rochelle ended that city’s status as a military “safe haven” designated by two letters patent accompanying this law. The subjects of this law were given refuge by the Edict of Potsdam after this law was revoked by Louis XIV in the Edict of Fontainebleau. For ten points, name this law promulgated by Henry IV which granted some tolerance to Huguenots in France.",
        "answer": "Edict of Nantes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Religious intolerance in France would only be legally fully lifted by what document written by the Comte de Mirabeau and the Marquis de Lafayette during the French Revolution?",
        "answer": "Declaration of the Rights of Man and the Citizen"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At one of these locations, Mario Savio urged listeners to “put your bodies upon the gears.” Roslyn Pope drafted “An Appeal for Human Rights” in the aftermath of a series of 1960 protests at one of these locations. John Filo won a Pulitzer for a picture taken at one of these institutions showing a Mary Ann Vecchio kneeling over the body of Jeffery Miller. Marshall Sahlins, in protest of the Vietnam War, developed the concept of a “teach-in” at one of these institutions in Ann Arbor. For ten points, name these institutions of higher education.",
        "answer": [
          "universities",
          "colleges"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Jeffery Miller was shot to death by the Ohio National Guard while attending what university?",
        "answer": "Kent State University"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The first ruler of this name convinced the Khan of Sarai that his son Simeon The Proud should succeed him as Grand Duke of Vladimir. Another ruler with this name defeated Ahmad Khan during a standoff on the Ugra River, ending Tatar rule over his lands. The fourth ruler of this name signed the Treaty of Jam Zapolski to end the Livonian War and established the oprichnina. For ten points, give the common name of several Rurikid rulers of Muscovy with epithets including “the Terrible.”",
        "answer": [
          "Ivan",
          "Ivan I Kalita",
          "“Moneybags”, Ivan III the Great, Ivan IV the Terrible"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As first Tsar of Russia, Ivan the Terrible convened the first meeting of this parliamentary body in 1549. This assembly represented all of Russia’s feudal class, including the nobles, the clergy, and the commoners.",
        "answer": "Zemsky Sobor"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The uncle of this man was killed and had his liver taken as a prize at the Battle of Uhud. In the Story of the Cranes, this person was said to have initially accepted the idols Lat, Manat, and Uzza. This person fled one city on the horse Buraq, and was married to Aisha. Jibreel aided this person during the Battle of Badr, and during the Night Journey, this person lowered the required number of prayers from 50 to 5 per day. For ten points, name this man, the final prophet and founder of Islam.",
        "answer": "Muhammad"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The incident involving the acceptance of the gods Lat, Manat, and Uzza takes this name, which was the inspiration for the title and plot of a novel by Salman Rushdie.",
        "answer": "The Satanic Verses"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "U.S. Colleges and Universities",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Ivy League school in Cambridge, Massachusetts that hosts the Kennedy School of Government.",
          "answer": "Harvard University"
        },
        {
          "question": "Flagship state university located in Charlottesville and founded by Thomas Jefferson.",
          "answer": [
            "University of Virginia",
            "UVA"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Connecticut university where George W. Bush was a member of the Skull and Bones Society.",
          "answer": "Yale University"
        },
        {
          "question": "Public university where Gerald Ford played football in Ann Arbor.",
          "answer": "University of Michigan"
        },
        {
          "question": "West Coast university located in Eugene where Bill Bowerman and Phil Knight met before founding Nike.",
          "answer": "University of Oregon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Catholic university in Indiana whose former staff includes Knute Rockne [newt ROCK-nee] and Joseph Buttigieg [BOOT-eh-jedge].",
          "answer": "University of Notre Dame"
        },
        {
          "question": "Formerly tuition-free Manhattan college that was the site of a famous 1860 Abraham Lincoln speech.",
          "answer": [
            "Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art",
            "Cooper Institute"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Missouri college where Winston Churchill discussed the Iron Curtain in his “Sinews of Peace” speech.",
          "answer": "Westminster College"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Nazi Sympathizers and Supporters",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Austrian-American bodybuilder and governor, whose father joined the Nazi Party.",
          "answer": "Arnold Schwarzenegger"
        },
        {
          "question": "Papal name of Joseph Ratzinger, a one-time member of the Hitler Youth.",
          "answer": "Benedict XVI"
        },
        {
          "question": "Woman who directed the Nazi propaganda film Triumph of the Will.",
          "answer": "Leni Riefenstahl"
        },
        {
          "question": "Composer of the opera Der Rosenkavalier who took an official music position in the Third Reich.",
          "answer": "Richard Strauss"
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian UN Secretary General whose political career suffered from his past Nazi associations.",
          "answer": "Kurt Waldheim"
        },
        {
          "question": "Philosopher of Being and Time who was classified as a mitl¨aufer, or passive Nazi supporter.",
          "answer": "Martin Heidegger"
        },
        {
          "question": "Painter, a member of Die Bru¨cke [dee BROOK-uh], whose works were recently removed from the chancellor’s office by Angela Merkel.",
          "answer": "Emil Nolde"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nazi Party member who served as principal conductor of the Berlin Philharmonic for 35 years.",
          "answer": "Herbert von Karajan"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Nefertiti",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "RoyalEgyptianpositionshemayhaveheldunderthemalenameNeferneferuaten[nefer-nefer-oo-aten].",
          "answer": "pharaoh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Husband of Nefertiti, who promoted the worship of the sun disc.",
          "answer": "Akhenaten or Amenhotep IV"
        },
        {
          "question": "Burial valley near Thebes where Nefertiti is believed, but not yet proven, to be buried.",
          "answer": "Valley of the Kings"
        },
        {
          "question": "Number of the dynasty in which she ruled, the first dynasty of the New Kingdom.",
          "answer": "18th Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of sculpture of the head and neck, a famous one of which depicts Nefertiti.",
          "answer": "bust"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where that sculpture is now located in the Neues [noy-us] Museum.",
          "answer": "Berlin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name for an ancient monumental slab of rock that is often inscribed; on the Coregency example, Nefertiti’s name is crossed out.",
          "answer": "stele or stela"
        },
        {
          "question": "Predecessor of Neferneferuaten as leader; he briefly succeeded Nefertiti’s husband.",
          "answer": "Smenkhkare"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. Legal authorities began their policy of not disclosing victims’ names after Maria Elena learned about this event from watching television. Waylon Jennings and Tommy Allsup continued the (20 pts)",
        "“Winter Dance Party” tour despite this event, which Allsup allegedly avoided by losing a coin toss, a story depicted in the film La Bamba. This event is presumed to be the (10 pts)",
        "“bad news on the doorstep” in Don McLean’s “American Pie.” For ten points, name this event that resulted in the deaths of J.P. Richardson, Ritchie Valens, and the lead singer of The Crickets."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Day the Music Died",
        "answers describing the plane Crash that killed Buddy Holly",
        "equivalent for plane crash"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country’s Red Week strikes were supported by the PSI, whose own members were split into the Reformist and Maximalist factions. Troops belonging to this country were massacred in (20 pts)",
        "Tripoli by the Ottomans, and this country entered a war after being promised South Tyrol in the Treaty of London. Failed negotiations over (10 pts)",
        "Fiume prompted this country’s Prime Minister Vittorio Orlando to quit the Paris Peace Conference prematurely. A retreat from Caporetto was a disaster for, for ten points, what country whose king Victor Emmanuel III joined the Allies in WWI in 1915?"
      ],
      "answer": "Kingdom of Italy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first entry on the QV catalog contains around 200 works for this instrument. Paul Taffanel was the dedicatee of a D major concertino for this instrument by Cecile Chaminade, while Johann Joachim (20 pts)",
        "Quantz was a prolific composer for it. A work this instrument is named for a property of platinum, Density 21.5, and is by Edgard Var`ese. This instrument plays a chromatic descent to open (10 pts)",
        "Debussy’s Prelude to the Afternoon of a Faun. Frederick the Great was a virtuoso of, for ten points, what transverse woodwind instrument, a larger relative of the piccolo?"
      ],
      "answer": "flute"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Robert Bellah used a quote from this book to title his Habits of the Heart. Louis Hartz opened The Liberal Tradition in America with a quote from this book about a country where people are (20 pts)",
        "“born equal” rather than “becoming equal.” In a section titled for the “Three Races” of its title country, this book predicts a race war between blacks and (10 pts)",
        "whites. The author of this book traveled with Gustave de Beaumont in 1831 to investigate the title country’s prison system. For ten points, name this book written by Alexis de Tocqueville about the political system of the United States."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "On Democracy in America",
        "De La Democratie en Amerique"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was betrayed by Quintus Catulus after he was accused of taking all the credit for a victory at Vercellae. After this man pacified the Teutones at Aquae Sextiae and repelled the (20 pts)",
        "Cimbri, he became known as the “third founder of Rome.” This man eliminated the use of the mandible formation and reorganized the (10 pts)",
        "legions into separate cohorts. This man served a record seven consulships, during which he allowed landless citizens to fight in the army as part of his namesake reforms. For ten points, identify this Roman general who was a rival of Lucius Cornelius Sulla."
      ],
      "answer": "Gaius Marius"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) James Seagrove helped one revolutionary from this country escape to the United States where he met Susan Livingston. That man from this country earned the temporary rank of lieutenant colonel while attacking Fort Pensacola and was later arrested by (20 pts)",
        "Bernardo de G´alvez for invading the Bahamas. Another revolutionary from this country revived a republic in this country after issuing the (10 pts)",
        "Cartagena Manifesto and conducting the Admirable Campaign. Francisco de Miranda was a sometimes ally of Sim´on Bol´ıvar in fighting for the independence of, for ten points, what country?"
      ],
      "answer": "Venezuela"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Henry Leland started a company in this state which he later left after a dispute with William Durant over the creation of Liberty aircraft engines. An executive in this state, (20 pts)",
        "William Knudsen, was allowed to join the army as a Lieutenant General and was appointed by Franklin Roosevelt as the Director of Production. In 1941, construction began on the (10 pts)",
        "Willow Run plant in this state which produced hundreds of B-24 bombers. This state was home to the River Rouge complex which, while originally constructed for World War I, built nearly every part of the Model T. For ten points, name this state where companies like General Motors and Ford were key in wartime production."
      ],
      "answer": "Michigan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) R. R. Palmer pioneered the historiography of this body of water in a work that advanced the comparative approach to studying this body of water. That book blamed shared political (20 pts)",
        "troubles and ideas across this body of water for its titular events and was called The Age of Democratic Revolutions. One economic model of this body of water includes the export of (10 pts)",
        "tobacco and sugar produced by imported slaves in Caribbean colonies. The Triangle Trade occurred on, for ten points, what body of water which separated Europe from its empires in Africa and the Americas?"
      ],
      "answer": "The Atlantic Ocean"
    }
  ]
}